Richard Wilson Papers
Richard Wilson Papers
1870-1987
Wilson, Richard, 1920-1987
15.5 linear ft.
Correspondence, financial and legal material, memorabilia, fanzines, and writings including short stories, plays, novels, novellas, and miscellaneous items.
148760
Biographical History
Richard "Dick" Wilson (1920-1987) was an American journalist and science fiction author. His "Mother to the World" won the 1968 Nebula Award for best novelette.
Wilson graduated from high school at 15. He served in the U.S. Army Signal Corps during World War II, stationed in the South Pacific with the 339th Fighter Squadron/347th Fighter Group of the XIII AAF (now the Thirteenth Air Force). Following the war he worked for Transradio Press (1946-1951) and then for Reuter's (1951-1964). Later, he was director of the News Bureau at Syracuse University in Syracuse, New York.
Wilson's involvement with science fiction spanned most of his life. He was an early member of the Futurian Society, the influential New York City-based fan club founded in 1938, edited or co-edited seven fanzines in the late 1930s, published his first professional story in 1940, won a Nebula Award in 1968, and was instrumental in helping Syracuse University Libraries acquire the papers of many important science fiction authors and publishers in the 1970s.
Wilson was married twice: to Jessica Gould (1941-1944) and to Leslie Perri (1950-1967). Both were among the first female members of The Futurians and active in science fiction circles. Perri, born Doris Baumgardt, had previously been married to Frederik Pohl; she was also an author and artist, and a founding member of the Fantasy Amateur Press Association (FAPA). She and Wilson had one son, Richard David Wilson.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Richard Wilson Papers consists of correspondence, financial and legal material, memorabilia, printed material, subject files, and writings of the American science fiction author and journalist.
Correspondence contains incoming and outgoing correspondence, almost all of which pertains to some aspect of science fiction. Notable names represented in the collection include author and editor Frederik Pohl; author, agent, and "superfan" Forrest J Ackerman; author, editor, and publisher Don Wollheim; editor and agent E.J. Carnell; author and editor Tony Boucher; author, editor, critic, and writer's workshop creator Damon Knight; editor and publisher Leo Margulies and wife Cylvia; author and editor Robert A.W. Lowndes; authors Cyril Kornbluth, David Kyle, and Wilson "Bob" Tucker, among others. There is also a sizable amount of correspondence with publishers (Ace Books, Ballantine Books) and science fiction magazines (Amazing, Analog, Galaxy).
Financial and legal material consists of royalty statements from several publishers, and a few author's contracts. There is also a partnership agreement pertaining to the research and writing of a history of the 339th Fighter Squadron/347th Fighter Group.
Memorabilia includes awards, clippings about Wilson and about Syracuse University's science fiction collections, convention material (including eleven WorldCons), family papers and photographs, and scrapbooks. There is also a substantial amount of material relating to Wilson's service during World War II, including ship and squadron newspapers, photographs, and Japanese-issued scrip for several occupied regions. There is also a special issue of James V. Taurasi's fanzine "Fantasy Times" entitled "Fantasy Times in France" (Taurasi served in the U.S. Army, 1942-1946). There are also two toy ray-guns and a tiny plastic toy missile mounted on a ring.
Printed material consists primarily of fanzines, in most cases only a few issues of any given title. Titles represented include Algol, Lobster Tails, and the fanzines of Mae Strelkov (Tink, Tong, and The Tunkunaku Event).
Subject files relate primarily to potential or actual writing projects, such as the 347th/339th Fighter Group of the XIII Army Air Force and flying saucers/UFOs. There is also some Reuter's material and a folder of material about Frederik Pohl.
Writings, which makes up almost half the collection, contains articles, books (both novels and novellas), plays, reviews (film and theater), and short stories by Wilson. Formats for a given title may include notes, research material, early drafts, later drafts, final drafts, galleys, and published versions. In many cases there is a typed note from Wilson giving the dates during which a piece was written and worked on. Miscellaneous items include one issue of Wilson's own fanzine, "Escape", and notes from several trials that he covered while working for Transradio Press, including that of Mildred Gillars, known as "Axis Sally." At the end of this series are a few items by others, including the final manuscripts for two novels by Ken Bulmer and a typed draft of a piece by H.P. Lovecraft.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, and within that chronologically. Writings are subdivided by type (articles, books, reviews, etc.) and within that are arranged alphabetically by title. Within each title, material is roughly in the order it would have been produced -- i.e., notes and research material, followed by earlier drafts, later drafts, galleys, and published version. All other series are arranged alphabetically by type or topic.
Related Material
Our holdings include papers from a number of well-known science fiction authors. Please refer to for more information.
Separated Material
A few published books and magazines have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Science fiction; Journalism; Military history; Literature -- American Fiction; Ackerman, Forrest J.; Anderson, Poul, 1926-2001.; Blish, James.; Boucher, Anthony, 1911-1968.; Bulmer, Kenneth, 1921-2005.; Burbee, Charles.; Cannon, Thurlow O.; Carnell, John, 1912-1972.; Cogswell, Theodore R.; Gillars, Mildred, 1900-1988.; Greenberg, Martin Harry.; Gunn, James E., 1923-2020.; Harrison, Harry, 1925-2012.; Kidd, Virginia.; Knight, Damon Francis, 1922-2002.; Kornbluth, C. M. (Cyril M.), 1923-1958.; Krause, Julius.; Kyle, David A.; Lovecraft, H. P. (Howard Phillips), 1890-1937.; Lowndes, Robert A. W. (Robert Augustine Ward), 1916-1998.; Margulies, Leo, 1900-1975.; Merril, Judith, 1923-1997.; Moskowitz, Sam.; Pohl, Frederik.; Santessen, Hans.; Strelkov, Mae.; Tucker, Wilson, 1914-2006.; Vonnegut, Kurt.; Williamson, Jack, 1908-2006.; Wilson, Felicitas K.; Wilson, Richard, 1920-1987.; Wollheim, Donald A.; Ace Books.; Ballantine Books (Firm); Eastern Science Fiction Association.; First Fandom.; Reuters Limited.; Science Fiction Writers of America.; Syracuse University. -- Libraries.; Transradio Press.; United States. -- Army Air Forces. -- Air Force, 13th. -- Fighter Squadron, 339th.; World Science Fiction Convention.; Magazine of fantasy and science fiction (Cornwall, Conn.); Galaxy.; Schlaraffia Zeyttungen.; American literature -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Novelists, American.; Playwrights, American.; Science fiction -- Periodicals.; Science fiction conventions.; Science fiction films.; Science fiction, American.; Ship newspapers.; Unidentified flying objects.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Aerial operations.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Ocean.; Articles.; Books.; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Contracts.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Fanzines.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Military maps.; Military records.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Reviews (documents); Royalty statements.; Scrapbooks.; Scrip (paper money); Short stories.; Toys (recreational artifacts); Authors.; Journalists.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Folders in boxes 13 and 14 pertaining to the 339th Fighter Squadron/347th Fighter Group are closed to researchers pending review.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Richard Wilson, 1967-1987.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Ace Books, 1956-1957; 1965,; 1970,; 1978-1979; Don Wollheim, Jim Baen (Box 1)
  - Ackerman, Forrest, 1958-1960; 1965-1977,; 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Amazing, 1953; 1961; Howard Browne, Cale Goldsmith (Box 1)
  - Amazing-Fantastic Publications, See Malzberg, Barry.
  - American-International Pictures, 1960-1961; regarding movie adaptation of Girls from Planet 5; includes Wilson's comments on screenplay (Box 1)
  - Analog, 1961; 1966,; 1972-1973; John Campbell, Ben Bova (Box 1)
  - Anderson, Poul, 1969; includes photo of Anderson taken by Jay Kay Klein (Box 1)
  - Ann Elmo (literary agency), 1955 (Box 1)
  - Arkoff, Samuel Z., See American-International Pictures.
  - Arney, J. Ward, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - Asimov, Isaac, 1953-1954; 1960,; 1966-1975 (Box 1)
  - Astounding, 1953; undated; John Campbell (Box 1)
  - Authentic Science Fiction Monthly, 1953-1955; H.J. Campbell (Box 1)
  - A, misc (Box 1)
  - Ballantine Books, 1953-1965; 1968,; 1975,; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Benton & Bowles, Inc., 1969; about film rights to "Mother to the world" (Box 1)
  - Biggle, Lloyd, 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - Blish, James, 1957-1958; 1968 (Box 1)
  - Blish, Virginia Kidd, See Kidd, Virginia.
  - Boucher, Anthony, See Mercury Publications.
  - Bova, Ben, See OMNI.
  - Bruck, Arline S., 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Bulmer, Ken, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Burbee, Charles, 1945 (Box 1)
  - B, misc (Box 1)
  - Campbell, John, See Astounding, Analog.
  - Cannon, Thurlow, 1967; 1970 (Box 1)
  - Capitol Records, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Carnell, E.J., 1955-1957; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Carnell, E.J., 1958-1972; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Carr, Terry, 1971; 1979-1980; most relates to him as editor of Universe (Box 2)
  - Cogswell, Theodore, 1960; 1963,; 1967,; 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Collier's, 1953-1955; undated (Box 2)
  - Collins, Christine H., 1944-1945 (Box 2)
  - Columbia Records, 1951 (Box 2)
  - C, misc (Box 2)
  - Dale Books, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Day, Donald, 1952; Perri Press (Box 2)
  - Dollens, Morris Scott, 1970-1971; includes some printed material with Dollens' art (Box 2)
  - Doubleday, 1955; 1965-1967,; 1969,; 1972; Larry Ashmead, others (Box 2)
  - Dowling, Eddie, 1958; 1965 (Box 2)
  - Dunkelbarger, Janet, 1970-1983; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - D, misc, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Eastern Science Fiction Association (Box 2)
  - Elliott, George P., 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - E, misc (Box 3)
  - Fantasy & Science Fiction, 1952-1979; includes editor Anthony (Tony) Boucher; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Fass, Martin, 1952; 1955,; 1965,; 1967,; 1981,; undated (Box 3)
  - First Fandom, 1982 (Box 3)
  - F, misc (Box 3)
  - Galaxy, 1953-1972; 1978,; undated; 4 folders (Box 3)
    See also Pohl, Frederik, above.
  - Geis, Richard E., 1970-1974; 1977 (Box 3)
  - Gold, Horace, See Galaxy.
  - Goulart, Ron, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Gray, James, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Greenberg, Martin, 1977-1981 (Box 3)
  - Grennell, Dean A., 1955; editor of Grue (Box 3)
  - Gunn, James, 1972; 1977 (Box 3)
  - G, misc (Box 3)
  - Hamilton, Edmond, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Harbottle, Philip, 1970; 1973,; 1975 (Box 3)
  - Harrison, Harry, 1953-1954; 1966-1967,; 1969,; 1972 (Box 3)
  - Horwitz, Howie, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Hydra Club, 1949; New York City fan club (Box 3)
  - H, misc (Box 3)
  - Iadeluca, Robert, 1975-1981; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Institute of Twenty First Century Studies, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Isaac Asimov's Science Fiction Magazine, 1977-1981; George Scithers, Jack Gaughan (Box 4)
  - I, misc (Box 4)
  - Jakes, John, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Kidd, Virginia, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - King, Harold, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - The Kirmess [journal], 1962 (Box 4)
  - Knight, Damon, 1956-1977; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Kornbluth, Cyril, 1943-1945; 1949-1954,; 1958,; 1966,; 1968; includes handwritten notes by Wilson on his memories of Kornbluth (Box 4)
    See also Transradio Press.
  - Kyle, David, 1942-1951; 1955,; 1960,; 1963-1973; 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Kyle, David, 1973-1981; undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - K, misc (Box 5)
  - Lang, Fritz, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Lewis, Jack, 1957-1958; regarding his "Who's Who in Science Fiction" (Box 5)
  - Linard, Jean and Anie, 1958; undated (Box 5)
  - Lowndes, Robert A.W., 1938; 1950-1959,; 1968-1969 (Box 5)
  - L, misc (Box 5)
  - Mahaffey, Bea, See Palmer, Ray.
  - Malzberg, Barry, 1968; 1978; editor, Amazing-Fantastic Publications (Box 5)
  - Mangan, James T., 1956-1957 (Box 5)
  - Margulies, Leo and Cylvia, 1941; 1954-1958; owners/editors of King-Size Publications, Renown Publications (Box 5)
  - McCaffrey, Anne, 1969 (Box 5)
    See also Science Fiction Writers of America.
  - McComas, J. Francis, 1968-1969; 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    See also Fantasy & Science Fiction.
  - Mercury Publications, 1946; 1953-1958; titles mentioned include Ellery Queen Mystery Magazine, Venture Science Fiction (Box 5)
  - Merril, Judy, 1950; 1960-1969,; 1971 (Box 5)
  - Miley, James D., 1973 (Box 5)
  - Miller, P. Schuyler, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Moore, Roz and Bill, 1968-1975 (Box 5)
  - Moskowitz, Sam, 1966 (Box 5)
    See also Science Fiction Plus.
  - M, misc (Box 5)
  - N, misc (Box 5)
  - Olander, Joseph, See Greenberg, Martin
  - OMNI magazine, 1979; Ben Bova, Robert Sheckley (Box 5)
  - O, misc (Box 5)
  - Pace, Mary, 1946 (Box 5)
  - Palmer, Ray, 1953-1957; Palmer Publications; titles mentioned include Mystic, Universe, Science Stories. (Box 5)
  - Peters, George R., See Miley, James D.
  - Playboy, 1955-1957; 1969,; 1982,; undated (Box 5)
  - Pohl, Frederik, 1940; 1944-1954; wife Dorothy; sometimes addressed to/signed by Pohl as "Ø" (phi, for Fred); includes remarks by Wilson about Pohl; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Pohl, Frederik, 1955-1957; 1966-1977,; 1980-1981,; undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - P, misc (Box 6)
  - QM Productions, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Quinn, James L., 1953; 1956; Quinn Publishing, publisher of If (Box 6)
  - Rappoport, Jack (Jacob L.), 1946-1949 (Box 6)
  - Regan, Michael Vincent, 1970; relates to Delphi Method project with SF authors; includes Jack Dann, Greg Benford (Box 6)
  - Reuters, 1952; 1954,; 1964 (Box 6)
    See also Subject files: Reuters.
  - Rubin, Arthur, 1944-1945 (Box 6)
  - R, misc (Box 6)
  - Salinger, Pierre, 1961 (Box 6)
  - Santessen, Hans, 1956-1957; 1960,; 1967,; 1969-1970 (Box 6)
  - Science Fiction Plus, 1953-1954; Gernsback Publications; Sam Moskowitz (Box 6)
  - Science Fiction Writers of America (SFWA)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1978; 1981-1982; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Directories, 1973-1978; 1981 (Box 6)
    - SFWA Bulletin, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
    - SFWA Forum, 1967-1971; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - SFWA Forum, 1974; 1976-1977,; 1981-1982; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Scithers, George, 1958 (Box 7)
  - Shaw, Larry, 1950-1958; 1963-1970,; undated; Quinn Publishing; Royal Publications (Box 7)
  - Skelton, Frank, 1958 (Box 7)
  - Smith, E.E. ("Doc"), Mrs., 1966; his widow (Box 7)
  - Speer, Jack (Juffus), 1944-1945; 1969-1971 (Box 7)
  - Standard Magazines, 1940-1941; 1954; T.W. Raines (Box 7)
  - Stern, George, 1943-1945; 1954,; 1964-1965 (Box 7)
  - Strelkov, Mae, See Printed material: Fanzines.
  - Sykora, Will, See Hydra Club.
  - Syracuse University Libraries, Manuscript Division, 1964-1970; 1976,; undated; includes one folder of published material (booklets, etc.); 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Szarat, Henry T. (Hank), 1944-1945 (Box 7)
  - S, misc (Box 7)
  - Tappan Zee National Bank, 1958-1960; relates to exhibit of local authors; includes copy of Authors of Rockland County (Box 7)
  - Timewell, Vin and Anne, 1971-1973 (Box 8)
  - Transradio Press, 1948-1952; includes sheet with list of personnel (Box 8)
  - Tsunoda, Waka, 1968 (Box 8)
  - Tucker, Bob (Wilson), 1945-1949; 1952-1955,; 1960,; 1964-1965; includes amusing floor plan for Tucker Fan Hotel and reprint of Tau Ceti newsletter from ChiCon I (1940 WorldCon) (Box 8)
  - T-U, misc (Box 8)
  - Van Houten, Ray, 1955 (Box 8)
  - Veteran (magazine), 1946 (Box 8)
  - Vonnegut, Kurt, 1966 (Box 8)
  - Walker, Dale, 1967-1969; 1973,; 1978 (Box 8)
  - Williamson, Jack, 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - Wilson, Jessica E., 1944-1945 (Box 8)
  - Wollheim, Donald A., 1967; 1971-1973 (Box 8)
    See also Ace Books.
  - WorldCon invitations, 1959; 1969; invitations to participate in 17th and 27th WorldCons (Box 8)
  - WQED, 1955 (Box 8)
  - Wylie, Dirk, 1944-1945; literary agent (Box 8)
  - W, Y, misc (Box 8)
  - Zelazny, Roger, 1966 (Box 8)
  - Ziff-Davis, 1953-1957; 1961,; undated (Box 8)
  - First name only and unidentified (Box 8)
- Financial and legal material
  - Ace Books, 1960; 1964,; 1966; royalty reports (Box 8)
  - AMCO Films, 1959; contract for The girls from Planet 5 (Box 8)
  - Ballantine Books, 1953-1957; 1962; royalty reports, contracts (Box 8)
  - Copyright Office, 1969 (Box 8)
  - E.J. Carnell, 1954-1978; undated; royalty reports, Wilson's summary of income (Box 8)
  - Doubleday, 1978-1979; royalty reports, copies returned, etc. (Box 8)
  - Lancer Books, 1967-1969; royalty reports (Box 8)
  - Lightning Publications, 1946-1947; partnership agreement with other AAF members about writing history of 339th Fighter Squadron/347th Fighter Group (Box 8)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards
    - Nebula for Best Novelette, 1969; photograph of Wilson, program, clippings, etc. (Box 8)
    - Palawan Poetry-Prose award, 1945; 1969; photos, letters, copy of magazine (Box 8)
  - Clippings
    See also World War II: Clippings and Scrapbooks, below.
    - About Wilson, [1926?]; 1944-1945,; 1955-1958,; 1961-1962,; 1965-1970,; 1984 (Box 8)
    - About Syracuse University's science fiction collections, 1967; 1970,; 1973,; 1975 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1955; 1958,; 1961,; 1967; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Conventions
    - LunaCon, 1969-1971; 1974 (Box 9)
    - SFCon V, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Star Trek, 1973; 1975 (Box 9)
    - 11th WorldCon (PhilCon II), 1953 (Box 9)
    - 15th WorldCon (LACon I), 1957 (Box 9)
    - 24th WorldCon (TriCon), 1966 (Box 9)
    - 25th WorldCon (NYCon III), 1967 (Box 9)
    - 26th WorldCon (BayCon), 1968 (Box 9)
    - 27th WorldCon (St. LouisCon), 1969 (Box 9)
    - 28th WorldCon (HeiCon), 1970 (Box 9)
    - 31st WorldCon (TorCon II), 1973 (Box 9)
    - 33rd WorldCon (AussieCon), 1975 (Box 9)
    - 36th WorldCon (IguanaCon), 1978 (Box 9)
    - 37th WorldCon (SeaCon), 1979 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1952-1955; 1958,; 1961,; 1964-1970,; 1974,; 1982,; undated (Box 9)
  - The Dome, 1936; Richmond Hill High School yearbook (Box 10)
  - Family
    - Felicitas K. Wilson (mother)
      - College of Swedish Massage, 1951; diploma, class photograph (Oversize 2)
      - Correspondence, 1938; 1944-1945,; 1947,; 1953,; 1956 (Box 12)
      - "Notes for essays", typed and handwritten notes, fragments, drafts (Box 12)
      - Photographs (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous, 1919; 1944-1945,; 1950-1951,; 1955-1956; marriage certificate, College of Swedish Massage and other certifications, U.S. Power Squadron certificate, etc. (Box 12)
    - Richard Wilson (father)
      - Jephtha Lodge No. 494, 1918; undated; photographs, Master Mason certificates (2), membership cards (Oversize 2)
      - World War I service recognition, 310th Infantry, circa 1918 (Oversize 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1919; 1942,; 1944; honorable discharge from Army; membership cards; death and funeral documentation (Box 12)
    - Julius Krause (maternal grandfather)
      Much of this material is in German.
      - Manuscript, "Faith, greed, home", 1918; typed draft (Box 12)
      - Manuscript, "Gerold", undated; typed draft (Box 12)
      - Manuscript, "Stars and stripes among the Persians and Koords", undated; handwritten and typed drafts (Box 12)
      - Manuscript, "Verkauft", undated; handwritten and typed drafts and notes; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous, 1891; 1894,; undated; marriage certificate to Josephine Heller; citizenship certificate; items relating to Josephine's funeral; etc. (Box 12)
    - Eduard Krause (maternal great-grandfather), almost certainly Eduard Friedrich Heinrich Krause (1816-1882), printer and co-founder of the Berlin Craftsmen's Association
      - Printed material, circa 1870-1900 (Oversize 2)
        Originals of newspapers are VERY fragile. Do not handle. Use photocopies (in box).
        Zum jubilaeum ihres hochverehrten Meisters und Freundes EDUARD KRAUSE dargebracht vom personal der druckerei (1870) - quarto-size commemorative publication, in English "For the jubilee of esteemed master and friend Eduard Krause, offered by the staff of the print shop"
        Der Schlaraffia Zeyttungen no. 540 and 544 - newsletter of the Schlaraffia Society, a men's society founded in Prague in 1859 for purposes of friendship, art and humor (undated, probably circa 1890-1900
        National Zeitung No. 411 (1882)
    - Unidentified, formal portrait photographs of men and women, not identified but presumably family (Oversize 2)
  - Fantasy Calendar from Gnome Press, 1950 (Box 10)
  - "Jack and Jill" play, 1965; 1968,; 1985; clippings, letter, program from a performance, etc. (Box 10)
  - Missile ring, toy, small plastic ring with toy missile on it (Oversize 1)
  - Photograph of Wilson by Jay Kay Klein (Oversize 2)
  - Poster, "Spaceman Rose" by Josh Kirby
  - Ray guns, toy, circa 1950; 2 plastic ray guns (Oversize 1)
  - World War II
    - Clippings, 1943-1945; by Wilson, mostly letters home published in various outlets; about Wilson; miscellaneous (Box 12)
    - Currency, scrip issued by occupying Japanese forces as replacements for local currency in Philippines, Netherlands East Indies, Sarawak, etc. (Box 12)
    - Humor, miscellaneous, cartoons, joke articles/essays, etc.; includes photoreproduction of several cartoons done by Milton Caniff especially for the 339th Fighter Squadron and signed/inscribed to Wilson and the men (Box 12)
    - Maps, circa 1943; printed on silk, likely used by/belonged to pilots (Oversize 1)
    - Official communications, 1942-1945; Wilson's draft notice, official orders, transfer orders, etc. (Box 12)
    - Oldsmobile ad, featuring the "Gremlin" of the 339th (Oversize 2)
    - Ship and squadron newspapers, 1944-1945 (Box 12)
      "The G.I Afloat," unspecified ship
      "The Mariner", unspecified ship, vol. 1 no. 1-3, 5-8
      "The Stateside Express," USS Wharton, no. 1-17
      "Sun Setter," XIII AAF Fighter Command, 5 issues, most incomplete, and packet of typescript revisions
      "Voice of A-2," Casual Squadron A-2, no. 1
      "The Tropic-Optic," 38th Air Service Squadron, vol. 2 no. 4
    - Miscellaneous, photographs, cancelled checks, leaflet dropped on Japanese announcing end of war, issue of "Fantasy Times in France" by James V. Taurasi, other items (Box 13)
  - Scrapbooks, clippings, book jackets, reviews, etc., relating to science fiction books and movies
    - "Science fiction films and plays", 1937 (Box 10)
    - "Science fiction scrapbook", 1937-1938 (Box 10)
    - "Fantasy films of 1938", 1938-1939 (Box 10)
    - "Off-trail plays", 1938-1939 (Box 10)
    - "Off-trail plays", 1939 (Box 10)
  - "Yankee Hobo in the Orient" map, printed version of map drawn by author John Patric to go with his book; signed and inscribed (Oversize 2)
  - Miscellany, membership cards, press pass, artwork, etc. (Box 10)
- Printed material
  - Fanzines
    - Algol, 1972; no. 18 (Box 10)
    - The Chief Procurer Speaks, 1977; vol. 3 no. 5 (Box 10)
    - Escape, See Writings: Miscellaneous: Wilson fanzine, "Escape".
    - Fantasy Times, 1952-1953; vol. 3 no. 4; vol. 7 no. 4, 9 (Box 11)
      See also Memorabilia: World War II: Miscellaneous.
    - The Gridley Wave, 1965; no. 17 (Box 11)
    - The Hamm Court Herald, 1970; no. 1, no. 3 (Box 11)
    - Heroine's Showcase Art Portfolio, 1979; no. 2 (Box 11)
    - The Innavigable Mouth, 1957-1958; no. 3, no. 4 (Box 11)